A Finding Aid to the Milton Wolf Brown Papers, 1908-1998, in the Archives of American Art AAA.browmilt
Archives of American Art
Milton Wolf Brown papers
1908-1998
AAA.browmilt
Archives of American Art
26 Linear feet
The papers of art historian and educator Milton Wolf Brown date from 1908 to 1998 and measure 26.0 linear feet. The collection documents Brown's career through scattered biographical material, correspondence with friends, publishers, colleagues, artists, museums, and art organizations, travel journals, files for the Prendergast Catalogue Raisonne Project, exhibition, research, teaching, and organization files, printed material, and scattered photographs. A large portion of this collection consists of writings by Brown including notebooks, draft writings for books and other publications, lectures, and his writings as a student.
Brown, Milton Wolf
Provenance
The Milton Wolf Brown papers were donated in 2000 and 2001 by Blanche R. Brown, Brown's widow. Three reel-to reel sound recordings were lent for duplication to cassette and transcript in 1986 by Milton Brown. A cassette copy of the Martha Deane interview was donated in 2006 by Milton Brown's estate, via Naomi Rosenblum. Additional material was donated in 2002 and 2004 by Naomi Rosenblum, executor for the estate of Blanche R. Brown, who died in 2002.
Related Material
Also at the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Milton Wolf Brown, conducted in 1976 by Paul Cummings.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Milton Wolf Brown (1911-1998) was an art historian and educator in New York City.
Known to his friends as "Mainey," Brown was born in Brooklyn, New York, in 1911. At a young age he intended to be a painter and studied with Louis Lozowick. However, instead of attending art school, he entered New York University to study education and eventually received his master's and doctorate in art history from the Institute of Fine Arts. While there he took courses with Walter Friedlander, Erwin Panofsky, and Mayer Schapiro. He also received fellowships to the Courtauld Institute of Art in 1934 and Brussels in 1937, and studied from 1938-1939 at the Fogg Art Museum at Harvard University. In 1938 he married fellow student Blanche Levine. After serving in World War II, he began teaching in the art department at Brooklyn College in 1946. There he developed a specialization in American art history and his doctoral dissertation, American Painting from the Armory Show to the Depression, was published in 1955. In 1963 he participated in the fiftieth anniversary exhibition of the 1913 Armory Show. The publication of his book Story of the Armory Show coincided with this event.
In 1971 Brown established the graduate program in Art History at the City University of New York, which became preeminent in the areas of modern art and American art history. During the 1980s he remained a resident professor at CUNY, though he retired in 1979, and he held visiting professorships at Hebrew University in Jerusalem and the Center for Advanced Study in the Visual Arts at the National Gallery of Art. From 1983 to 1987 he had a senior fellowship at Williams College for the Prendergast Catalogue Raisonne Project.
Over the course of his career Brown curated exhibitions, including an exhibition on the works of Jacob Lawrence and The Modern Spirit: American Painting and Photography, 1908-1935, and wrote for numerous publications. He also served as an active member of several professional societies. Brown was close friends with art scholars and artists, such as Jack Levine, Moses and Raphael Soyer, Ad Reinhardt, and Paul Strand. In 1991 he returned to painting landscape watercolors, and had the opportunity to exhibit his work before his death in 1998.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of art historian and educator Milton Wolf Brown date from 1908 to 1998 and measure 25.8 linear feet. The collection documents Brown's career through scattered biographical material, correspondence with friends, publishers, colleagues, artists, museums, and art organizations, travel journals, files for the Prendergast Catalogue Raisonne Project, exhibition, research, teaching, and organization files, printed material, and scattered photographs. A large portion of this collection consists of writings by Brown including notebooks, draft writings for books and other publications, lectures, and his writings as a student.
Biographical material includes academic records, travel documents, financial documents, Brown's military records, and a transcript of a 1997 interview. Correspondence is with students, museums, universities, publishers, art organizations, and others. The bulk of these letters document Brown's professional activities, but also found are scattered letters from friends, artists, and colleagues such as Russell Lynes, Stanley Meltzoff, Louis Lozowick, Erwin Panofsky, and Paul Sachs.
This collection also contains 33 detailed travel journals written primarily by Milton Brown's wife, Blanche, documenting their travels in Europe, the United States, and other parts of the world. Within the writings series are notebooks from the period that Brown was a student and while traveling in Europe in 1959 and 1960; book project files, which include draft writings as well as related correspondence, research material, notes, photographs and other material. Files are found for American Art: Painting, Sculpture, Architecture, Decorative Arts, Photography (1979), American Painting, From the Armory Show to the Depression (1955), The Story of the Armory Show (1963, 1988 2nd ed.), and other books. Among the writings are files for lectures written by Brown; essays, articles, and scripts written for various publications; general research notes and student writings; and writings by others sent to Brown for review and feedback.
Brown maintained a set of files documenting his work on the Prendergast Catalogue Raisonne Project, which consist of correspondence, drafts, reports, and research materials, including notes on twenty meetings with Mrs. Prendergast. Exhibition files document Brown's work as curator on several major exhibitions, including a Jacob Lawrence exhibition at the Whitney Museum, and his contributions to others. Also found here are three interviews of Milton Brown and Marcel Duchamp concerning the 50th Anniversary of the Armory Show and anniversary exhibition. Research files include notes, research material, and printed material on various art-related subjects that were maintained by Milton and Blanche Brown for regular use for lectures, teaching, and writing projects. Brown's teaching files contain scattered lecture notes, syllabi, correspondence, faculty records, and other materials from his time at CUNY, Brooklyn College, and other visiting professorships. Organization Files contain correspondence, reports, planning documents, and event materials. These records document his membership or advisory role in various organizations such as the Archives of American Art and Century Association.
This collection also contains printed material, such as exhibition announcements, newsletters, brochures, journals, event programs, and magazine and newspapers clippings compiled by Brown. Scattered photographs include nine photographs of Milton Brown, a few photographs of friends, and photographs of artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 11 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1932-1998 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1908, 1934-1998 (Boxes 1-3; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Travel Journals, 1941-1996 (Boxes 3-4; 1.6 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, circa 1929-1990s (Boxes 4-13, 25; 8.7 linear feet)
Series 5: Prendergast Catalogue Raisonne Project, circa 1952-1990 (Boxes 13-14, 25; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 6: Exhibition Files, 1962-circa 1997 (Boxes 14-16, 28; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 7: Research Files, circa 1930s-1986 (Boxes 16-19; 3.0 linear feet)
Series 8: Teaching Files, circa 1946-1993 (Boxes 19-21; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 9: Organization Files, 1959-1995 (Boxes 21-22; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 10: Printed Material, 1925-1990s (Boxes 22-24, 26, 27; 3.2 linear feet)
Series 11: Photographs, circa 1956-1990s (Boxes 25, 27; 0.2 linear feet)
Archives of American Art.; Brooklyn College Faculty; Brown, Blanche; Century Association (New York, N.Y.); City University of New York Faculty; Lawrence, Jacob, 1917-; Lozowick, Louis, 1892-1973; Lynes, Russell, 1910-1991; Meltzoff, Stanley; Panofsky, Erwin, 1892-1968; Prendergast, Charles, 1863-1948; Prendergast, Maurice Brazil, 1858-1924; Sachs, Paul; Whitney Museum of American Art.; Art historians--New York (State)--New York; Art, American History Sources; Articles; Curators--New York (State)--New York; Drafts (documents); Educators--New York (State)--New York; Essays; Interviews; Lectures; Notebooks; Photographs; Scripts (documents); Transcripts; Travel journals
- Biographical Material, circa 1932-1998; Series 1; (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material in this series includes academic and employment records for Milton Brown and his wife Blanche, biographical statements, files for grants, fellowships, and other study opportunities, and travel documents. Also found are scattered financial records, including documentation of the Brown's Art Nouveau collection and royalty statements for his books. Additionally, this series contains files kept by Brown documenting his military service, and a transcript of an interview of Brown conducted by Sally A. Duncan.
  Arrangement note
  Folders are arranged alphabetically. Items within each folder are arranged chronologically.
  - Academic Records and Curriculum Vitae, Blanche Levine Brown, circa 1938, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academic Records, Milton Wolf Brown, circa 1932-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bibliography, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Statements, circa 1955-1978, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Burglary Documentation, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Courtauld Institute Scholarship, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Employment Records, 1935-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fogg Museum Fellowship, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Financial Records, "Art Nouveau Purchases,", 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records, General, 1941-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Grant Applications, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - List of "Russian Friends,", undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorial Service Program, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Military Service, 1943-1946; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Documents, 1976-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - President's Medal, City University of New York, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Royalty Statements, 1955-1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Summer Study Abroad in Belgium, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Transcript, Interview of Milton Wolf Brown by Sally A. Duncan, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Travel Documents, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1908, 1934-1998; Series 2; (Box 1-3; 1.8 linear feet)
  This series contains Milton Brown's correspondence with family, his wife Blanche, friends, colleagues, students, museums, universities, publishers, and art organizations. Found here are two folders of letters Brown wrote to his family while studying in Europe, including his impressions of Germany and Russia. Also found are files of his correspondence with publishers, including Harry N. Abrams and Princeton University Press, and one file of correspondence with his friend, artist Jozef Pielage.
  The bulk of this series consists of Brown professional correspondence documenting his career as an art historian, writer and educator. Letters discuss his work on exhibitions, teaching, book projects, and lectures, and should be consulted in conjunction with Series 4: Writings, Series 6: Exhibition Files, and Series 8: Teaching files, which also contain related correspondence. Notable correspondents include artists and art historians such as Russell Lynes (1958, 1964, 1966, 1976, 1981, 1988, 1989), John Rewald (1988), Stanley Meltzoff (1968, 1971, 1981, 1982), Raphael Soyer (1972), Louis Lozowick (1943, 1963, 1967, 1969, undated), Joseph Hirshhorn (1963, 1966), Stephen Bourgeois (1963), Philip Evergood (1963), Maurice Becker (1962), Erwin Panofsky (1937, 1957, 1958), Paul Sachs (1939-1941, 1943, 1944, 1955), Everett Shinn (1944), and Meyer Schapiro (1935).
  Folders of select correspondence with family, Pielage, and publishers is filed according to Brown's original arrangement followed by general correspondence which is arranged chronologically.
  - Letters to Family, 1934, 1937; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Letters to Jozef and Betty Pielage, circa 1943-1977 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Elihu Vedder Letter given to Milton Brown by Ad Reinhardt, 1908, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence with Publishers (Box 1)
    - Chanticleer Press, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - G. K. Hall & Co., 1980-1990 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Harry N. Abrams, 1964-1984; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
    - Princeton University Press, 1949-1987; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
  - Draft Outgoing Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - General Correspondence, 1935-1971; (20 folders) (Box 1, Folder 33-52)
  - General Correspondence, 1972-1998; (22 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-22)
  - Undated Correspondence, circa 1940s-1990s; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
  - Christmas Cards, circa 1960s-1970s; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-28)
  - Christmas Cards, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Travel Journals, 1941-1996; Series 3; (Box 3-4; 1.6 linear feet)
  This series contains travel journals documenting Milton and Blanche Brown's trips throughout the United States, Europe, and other parts of the world. Most of these very detailed accounts were written by Blanche Brown.
  Journals are arranged chronologically. Folder headings are taken from titles written inside of each journal.
  - Cross Country Trip, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - New England, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - London to Paris, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - England, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - New England, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mexico, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Spain, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Europe, 1959-1960; (6 volumes in 3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
  - Europe, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - England and Italy, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - London and Italy, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Israel and Greece, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Sailing with Pete Phillipps, Maine, Paris, Burgundy, Edinburgh, Ireland, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Arts of Russia, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - China, Hong Kong, and Japan, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - England, Wales, and Scotland, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Israel, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Israel, Greece, Malta, and Italy, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - New York State, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Romania, Sardinia, and Rome, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Greek and Aegean Islands, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Portugal and Spain, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Milan, Turin, and Paris, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Tunisia, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Venice, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Morocco and Madrid, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Switzerland, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miami, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Writings, circa 1929-1990s; Series 4; (Boxes 4-13, 25; 8.7 linear feet)
  The series is arranged as 7 subseries:
  4.1: Notebooks, circa 1930-1977
  4.2: Book Projects, circa 1940-1987
  4.3: Lectures, circa 1950-1991
  4.4: Writings for Publication, 1943-1994
  4.5: General Research Notes and Writings, circa 1940s-1990s
  4.6: Student Writings and Notes, circa 1929-1939
  4.7: Writings by Others, circa 1930s-1991
  - Notebooks, circa 1930-1977; 4.1
    This subseries contains Milton Brown's notebooks, primarily from the period that he was in graduate school during the 1930s. Included are nine notebooks for specific art history courses he took while at NYU. Other notebooks found here include notes on art. Notebooks from 1959 and 1960 contain notes taken while Brown and his wife were traveling in Europe. Also found are three engagement calendars.
    - "French Painting 17th and 18th Century: Panofsky,", circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - "French Romanesque Sculpture: Schapiro,", circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - "Greek Sculpture: Lehmann-Hartleben,", circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - "Italian Renaissance Painting: Offner,", circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - "Medieval Architecture: Schapiro,", circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "Medieval Art: Morey,", circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Med. Mss.: Schapiro,", circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "Michelangelo Seminar: Panofsky,", circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - "Modern Painting: Schapiro,", circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Notebook, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Notebooks, circa 1930s; (7 folders) (Box 5, Folder 2-8)
    - "Art Nouveau Notes: Europe,", 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Notebooks, circa 1960; (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1974, 1976, 1977; (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 13-15)
  - Book Projects, circa 1940-1987; 4.2
    This subseries contains records of Milton Brown's book projects. Files for each project may consist of correspondence, draft versions, notes, research material, lists, photographs, and publicity and reviews. Correspondence found here discusses details for Brown's books and his research inquiries, and researchers should note that additional correspondence regarding these books may be found in Series 2: Correspondence. Among the correspondence regarding American Painting, From the Armory Show to the Depression are letters from Georgio O'Keeffe, Max Weber, Louis Lozowick, Charles Burchfield, Charles Sheeler, Andrew Dasburg, and William Gropper. Brown's book American Art to 1900 (1977) became part of the larger publication American Art: Painting, Sculpture, Architecture, Decorative Arts, and Photography so records for both books are filed together. Titles of works are arranged alphabetically and individual files are also arranged alphabetically.
    - American Art: Painting, Sculpture, Architecture, Decorative Arts, Photography (1979) (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1967-1975 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Correspondence, with Theresa Brakeley, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Draft 1, 1974; (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
      - Draft 2, undated; (3 of 5 folders) (Box 5, Folder 20-22)
      - Draft 2, undated; (2 of 5 folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
      - Draft 3, undated; (5 folders) (Box 6, Folder 3-7)
      - Draft 4, undated; (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
      - Draft Fragments, undated; (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 11-13)
      - List of Illustrations, circa 1969-1970s (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Notes and Research Material, circa 1969-1974 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Publicity and Reviews, 1977-1979; (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
      - "Review of Manuscript,", 1974 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - American Painting, 1913-1929: An Abridgment, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - American Painting, From the Armory Show to the Depression (1955) (Box 6)
      - Artwork Files, A-B, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - Artwork Files, C-Z, 1952-1953; (8 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
      - Bibliography, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1941, 1952-1956, 1973; (5 folders) (Box 7, Folder 10-14)
      - Draft Manuscript, circa 1940s; (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 15-16)
      - Footnotes, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 17)
      - Guggenheim Fellowship Application, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - Lists of Reproductions, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - Material for First Draft, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 20)
      - Outlines, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 21)
      - Notes, Armory Exhibition, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 22)
      - Notes, Art Magazines, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 23)
      - Notes, Ash Can School, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 24)
      - Notes, Biographical, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 25)
      - Notes, Camera Work, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 26)
      - Notes, Development of Taste, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 27)
      - Notes, Exhibitions, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 28)
      - Notes, General Background, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - Notes, Miscellaneous, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 30)
      - Notes, Private Collections, circa 1941 (Box 7, Folder 31)
      - Notes, Pseudo-Scientific Theories, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 32)
      - Notes, Stieglitz Group, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 33)
      - Notes, The Twenties, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 34)
      - Notes, War and Art, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 35)
      - Photographs and Reproductions of Artwork, circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 36)
      - Public Collections Lists, circa 1940-1941; (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 37-38)
      - Publicity and Reviews, 1955-1973 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Encyclopedia of Painting, Draft Entries, circa 1979; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Encyclopedia of Painting, Notes, circa 1979; (5 folders) (Box 8, Folder 3-7)
    - One Hundred Masterpieces of American Painting from Public Collections in Washington, D.C. (1983) (Box 8)
      - Corrected Proofs, circa 1980; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
      - Correspondence, 1981-1985 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Draft Captions, circa 1982; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
      - Miscellaneous Project Documents, circa 1982-1984 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      - Publicity and Reviews, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - The Story of the Armory Show (1963, 1988 2nd ed.) (Box 8)
      - "Alphabetical Listing of Works Included in the New York 1913 International Exhibition of Modern Art,", circa 1963 (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - Articles about the Armory Show (Photocopies), 1963-1984 (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - Contracts, 1962, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 17)
      - Correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box 8, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence with Hirshhorn Foundation, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence regarding Second Edition, 1985-1991; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 20-21)
      - Draft 1, circa 1963; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 22-23)
      - Draft 2, circa 1963 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - List of Reproductions, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Notes, Artists by Room, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Notes, Attendance, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Notes, Expenses and Payments, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Notes, Grafton Galleries, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Notes, J. Myers Papers, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Notes, Lenders, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Notes, McRae Papers, 1953, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Notes, Miscellaneous, circa 1960-1963 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Notes, Number of Works, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Notes, Pach Material, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Notes, Press, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Notes, Prints, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Notes, Schools, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Notes, Sonderbund Exhibition, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Notes, Walt Kuhn Papers, undated; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 17-18)
      - Payments to Assistants, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Photographs, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - "Preface to the Second Edition,", circa 1987 (Box 9, Folder 21)
      - Publicity, circa 1963, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 22)
      - Research Material (Photocopies), circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Lectures, circa 1950-1991; 4.3